Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. Collection, 1901-1977 (bulk 1908-1955)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. Collection, 1901-1977 bulk (1908-1950)
MS 543
Bonaventure, Father. O.F.M., 1885-1967
Consists of photocopies of chiefly correspondence, 1908-1950, of Franciscan missionary and historian Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. during his appointments, mainly to the Papago Indians (now known as Tohono O'odham), in Arizona. Included also are photographs that consist of images created by various Franciscan friars of the Saint Barbara Providence of the Order of Franciscan Friars depicting scenes from various Indian reservations in Arizona and Southern California. This collection also includes papers of Franciscan missionary, Nicholas Perschl (1887-1969), relating to his missionary work to the Papago Indians.
18 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Born in Portland, Oregon, on 7 March 1885, Emil Oblasser studied for the Franciscan priesthood (taking the name of Bonaventure) at Mission Santa Barbara from 1901 until 1908. After his ordination on 28 June 1908, his main assignments were:
1908-1910 St. Elizabeth Parish, Oakland
1910-1913 St. John's Mission, Komatke, Arizona
1913-1916 Mission San Xavier del Bac, Tucson
1916-1922 Old San Solano, Cababi, Arizona
1922-1939 New San Solano, Topawa, Arizona
1939-1941 Mission San Luis Rey, California
1941-1948 Santa Isabel Indian Mission, California.
His missionary work in Arizona resulted in the construction of over a dozen schools and churches on what would become known as the Papago Indian Reservation in southern Arizona. He was a member of the Committee that contributed to the formation of the reservation (1915), and he was a key advisor in both the legal battle against the Hunter Heirs in their claim to Papago Lands (1926) and in the formation of the tribal constitution (1936).
During his tenure, he gathered unique information on the Franciscan influence in Pimeria Alta, and collected censuses and other ethnological data on Indian populations. In the course of his research, he built a collection of books on the region which are now housed in the Oblasser Library at Mission San Xavier.
Father Oblasser celebrated the jubilee of his priesthood in 1958. He died in 1967 and was buried at the Topawa cemetery.
Nicholas Perschl (1887-1969) was ordained a Franciscan in 1913. He spent many years at Mission San Xavier del Bac, and he worked amongst the Papago, Pima, and Apache people in Arizona.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 5 series
Series 1:Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. Papers, 1908-1077
Sub-Series 1: Correspondence, 1908-1977
Sub-Series 2: Subject Files 1908-1977
Series 2: Photographs, 1902-1958
Series 3: Contact Sheets, circa 1923-1935
Series 4: Negatives, 1909-1960
Sub-Series 1: SX, undated
Sub-Series 2: SXB, undated
Sub-Series 3: Subjects, 1909-1960
Sub-Series 4: Glass Negatives, undated
Series 5: Nicholas Perschl Papers, 1901-1969
Scope and Content Note
These papers best document the activities of Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. in his daily struggles to secure the spiritual and financial needs of his missionary work to native peoples in California, and especially, Arizona. The bulk of the correspondence from 1908 to 1940 details his efforts to fund schools with supplies, furniture, and teachers, and to assist the Tohono O'odham in shaping their geographical and political future. The correspondence covers the spectrum of his work, including topics such as: administering to the vast expanse of the reservation; financing and constructing the buildings for religious and educational purposes; communicating with governmental officials and agencies on behalf of the Tohono O'odham on issues relating to the formation of the reservation, water, land and mineral rights; and assisting in the compilation of the tribal constitution.
There is also present some materials relating to censuses of various villages; Oblasser's annual reports to the Office of the Provincial on his accomplishments in the field; drafts of the Papago Constitution; his contributions to the erection of the Fray Marcos de Niza Monument near the Arizona-Mexico border; and many unpublished reports and articles that he wrote about Franciscan and Arizona history.
Correspondents in the collection include politicians Carl T. Hayden, George W.P. Hunt, Henry Ashhurst; government officials of the United States Bureau of Indian Affairs such as Charles Burke and John Collier; leaders of the Franciscan order and fellow missionaries in the field; support agencies for the missions such as the Bureau of Catholic Indian Missions, the Marquette League for Indian Welfare, and other private donors; scholars Herbert Bolton, Frank Lockwood, and others; and former students and friends.
The Subject Files contain correspondence, interviews, writings, and other records relating to various topics. Of interest are his missionary activities; a copy of Statuta Pro Missionibus: Ordinis Fratrum Minorum (1950); an interview (1959) of Oblasser by Bernard Fontana; censuses for the Saint John's Mission; and background information on San Jose Mission/Saint Nicholas Indian Center, and the San Xavier residence in Tucson. The largest folder of correspondence in these files relates to his work from 1956 to 1960 for the United States Department of Justice regarding the Papago Case Number 345 before the Indian Claims Commission for which he prepared an in-depth report on land tenure among the Papago Indians (however the report itself is lacking).
The photographic materials held within this collection are comprised of prints, negatives, contact sheets, and glass negatives. These materials are images created by various Franciscan friars of the Saint Barbara Providence of the Order of Franciscan Friars. These materials date probably from circa 1902-1958, with the bulk of the materials believed to date from circa 1920-1939. These materials were collected by Bonaventure Oblasser and held at the Oblasser Library at the Mission San Xavier del Bac.
The second series of papers relate to the personal life and career of Nicholas Perschl. Included are excerpts from his diary and autobiographical writings for his early years as a missionary; general correspondence from 1901 to 1969, chiefly with other Franciscans, former students, and friends; and letters (in German) from members of his extended family in Austria
Originals are located at the Santa Barbara Mission Library Archives, California. Duplicates are also held at San Xavier Mission Oblasser Library, Tucson, AZ 85745.
Researchers interested in materials related to Father Bonaventure Oblasser O.F.M. should consult the following collections held in the University of Arizona Special Collections Library:
AZ 397 - Oral history interview, Mission San Xavier del Bac, with Bernard Fontana, 1959 Jul. 20.
AZ 553 - Affidavit: the route followed by Fray Marcos de Niza which led to the discovery of Arizona, 1939.
AZ 554 - Diary and scrapbook of Mission San Xavier del Bac, 1861-1948
Researchers interested in materials related to Nicholas Perschl should consult the following collection:
AZ 396 - Oral history interview, Mission San Xavier del Bac, with Bernard Fontana, 1959 Jan. 26.
Access Terms
Bonaventure, Father, O.F.M., 1885-1967.
Perschl, Nicholas, 1887-.
Hayden, Carl Trumbell, 1877-1972
Mission San Xavier del Bac (Tucson, Arizona) - History
Missions - Arizona
Tohono O'Odham Indians - History
Tohono O'Odham Indian Reservation (Arizona) - History
Tohono O'Odham Indians - Government Relations
Tohono O'Odham Indians - Education
Franciscans - Arizona - Missions
Catholic Church - Arizona - Missions
Indians of North America—Pictorial works
Gila River Indian Reservation (Arizona) - History
San Xavier Indian Reservation (Arizona) - History
Container List
- Series 1: Oblasser Papers, 1908-1977
  These papers best document the activities of Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. in his daily struggles to secure the spiritual and financial needs of his missionary work to native peoples in California, and especially, Arizona. The series has two subseries. The first subseries contains correspondence that detail Father Bonaventure Oblasser's efforts to assist the Tohono O'odham in shaping their geographical and political future. The second subseries consists of subject files that contain correspondence, interviews, writings, and other records relating to various topics.
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence, 1908-1962
    This subseries contains correspondence. The bulks of these materials date from 1908 to 1940 and detail his efforts to fund schools with supplies, furniture, and teachers, and to assist the Tohono O'odham in shaping their geographical and political future. The correspondence covers the spectrum of his work, including topics such as: administering to the vast expanse of the reservation; financing and constructing the buildings for religious and educational purposes; communicating with governmental officials and agencies on behalf of the Tohono O'odham on issues relating to the formation of the reservation, water, land and mineral rights; and assisting in the compilation of the tribal constitution.
    - Correspondence, 1908-1923 (Box 1, Folder 1-15)
    - Correspondence, 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1933 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
    - Correspondence, 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1941 June (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence, 1941 July-1947 May (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
    - Correspondence, 1947 June-1951 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1962 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - Subseries 2: Subject Files, 1908-1977
    This subseries contains correspondence, interviews, writings, and other records relating to various topics. Of interest are his missionary activities; a copy of Statuta Pro Missionibus: Ordinis Fratrum Minorum (1950); an interview (1959) of Oblasser by Bernard Fontana; censuses for the Saint John's Mission; and background information on San Jose Mission/Saint Nicholas Indian Center, and the San Xavier residence in Tucson. The largest folder of correspondence in these files relates to his work from 1956 to 1960 for the United States Department of Justice regarding the Papago Case Number 345 before the Indian Claims Commission for which he prepared an in-depth report on land tenure among the Papago Indians (however the report itself is lacking).
    - Catholic Indian Outing Service, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Cross Over the Desert, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Education: Pimeria Alta, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Franciscans Take Charge of Yuma, Arizona, circa 1926 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Founding of Tucson, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Interview by Bernard Fontana, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Library of Piman Research, 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1942 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Missions/missionary activities, 1908-1952 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Mission Board, 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Prayers in Papago, 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Saint John's Mission Census, 1910-1912 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - San Jose Mission/Saint Nicholas Center (Tucson), 1977 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - San Xavier Historical Data, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - U. S. Department of Justice: Papago Tribe vs. U. S., Docket 345 Land Tenure Among the Papago, 1956-1960 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1902-1958
  This series consists of scenes from various Indian reservations where friars of the Saint Barbara Providence of the Order of Franciscan Friars served, including Papago, Gila River, Salt River, Ak Chin, Gila Bend, San Carlos, Ft. Apache, Mescalero, Ft. Yuma (Quechan), Colorado River, and various Native Communities in Southern California. Also included in this series are photographs of various locales and people taken on trips, including China, Sonoran Missions in Mexico, New Mexico, and California.
  - Ajo Deer Dancers, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Akin or Pisinere Church, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Anegam, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Buildings, 1916, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Bylar, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Cababi, St. Maria, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - California Missions, Various, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Casa Blanca, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - China, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Comobabi, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Covered Wells, 1912, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Cowlic, 1922, 1935, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Kaka, Gila Bend, 1919, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Komalik, Awegan, 1912 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Kwahatk, 1911-1912 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - La Jolla, California, 1940, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Little Tucson, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Lourdes School, Fresnal, Arizona, 1911-1913, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - McNary, Arizona, 1934 April (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Mission San Antonio de Pala, 1940, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Navajo, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Padres, 1920-1939 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Papgueria Baboquivari, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Pascua Yaqui, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - People, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Pima, circa 1939 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Pueblo Grande, circa 1940-1950 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Sacaton, circa 1932 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - San Carlos, Arizona, 1954 February, June (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - San Ignacio, 1915, undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - San Jose Pisinemo, 1915, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - San Luis Big Fields, 1912, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - San Miguel, 1911-1912, 1930-1953 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - San Pablo Chapel, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - San Pedro Coyote, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - San Solano, 1912 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - San Xavier del Bac, 1910, 1932, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Santa Rosa, 1912, 1913, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Santa Rosa, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Santan, 1937, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Sells, Arizona, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Sil Nakya, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - San Luis Rey Mission, California, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Scenery, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Sisters, 1936-1937 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - St. Boniface, Banning, California, 1936, 1938, undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - St. Clares Place, Portland, Oregon, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - St. John's, Kowatke Village, 1918-1958, undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - St. John's Indian School, Kowatke Village, 1922, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - St. John's Indian School, Kowatke Village, 1932, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - St. John's Indian School, Kowatke Village, 8x10s (1 of 2), undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - St. John's Indian School, Kowatke Village, 8x10s (2 of 2), undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - St. Michael's, 1934, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Topawa, 1902-1958 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Tumacacori, 1939, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Walls Well, San Martin, 1939, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Yaf Kük, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Yuma, Arizona (1 of 2), undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Yuma, Arizona (2 of 2), undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1905, 1938, 1952, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1920-1958, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1928, 1935, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943, 1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1944, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Contact Sheets, circa 1923-1935
  This series contains copy negatives from negative albums compiled by Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. These contact sheets were created using a 35mm camera with a close-up lens, and were created as access copies for the negatives series. The photograph albums have identifying numbers written on the verso with corresponding image identification within the photograph album index. Those contact sheets labeled SX and SXB correspond to materials held in the negatives series. These contact sheets do not act as a complete access tool for the negatives series, as all of the negatives have not been photocopied. The miscellaneous materials held within this series do not have any identifying information.
  - Photograph Album Index, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Photograph Album (1 of 2), circa 1923-1935 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Album (2 of 2), circa 1923-1935 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - SX-1 – SX161-5, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - SXB1-2 – SXB126-40, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - SXB127-40 – SXB243-75, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - SXB244-75 – SXB367-144, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - SXB368-144 – SXB493-205, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - SXB494-205 – SXB627-40, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - SXB628-241 – SXB778-319, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - SXB779-319 – SXB916-361, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - SXB917-361 – SXB1001-389, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - SXB1002-389 – SXB1067-408, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - SXB1068-409 – SXB1176-439, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - SXB1177-439 – SXB1258-468, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - SXB1259-469 – SXB1364-659, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - SXB1365-659 – SXB1456-677, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - SXB1457-671 – SXB1551-720, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - SXB1152-720 – SXB1604-685, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (1 of 2), undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (2 of 2), undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Series 4: Negatives, 1909-1960
  This series contains four subseries. The first subseries contains negatives that have corresponding access contact sheets from the contact sheet series. Materials in this subseries were numbered by Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. and have no particular order. The second subseries contains negatives that were originally held in negative albums compiled and numbered by Bonaventure Oblasser. The first identifying number is sequential and corresponds to total number of negatives in the subseries. The second identifying number corresponds to the number taken from Bonaventure Oblasser's original negative albums. The numbering system contains many numerical gaps. It is believed that these negatives were originally compiled chronologically by Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. The majority of materials in this subseries have corresponding access contact sheets contained in the Contact Sheet series. The third subseries contains negatives arranged alphabetically by subject. The majority of materials in this subseries are unidentified. The fourth subseries contains unidentified glass negatives.
  - Subseries 1: SX, undated
    This subseries contains negatives that have corresponding access contact sheets from the contact sheet series. Materials in this subseries were numbered by Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. and have no particular order.
    - SX1-1 – SX66-3, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - SX67-3 – SX109-5, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - SX110-5 – SX161-5, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: SXB, undated
    This subseries contains negatives that were originally held in negative albums compiled and numbered by Bonaventure Oblasser. The first identifying number is sequential and corresponds to total number of negatives in the subseries. The second identifying number corresponds to the number taken from Bonaventure Oblasser's original negative albums. The numbering system contains many numerical gaps. It is believed that these negatives were originally compiled chronologically by Father Bonaventure Oblasser, O.F.M. The majority of materials in this subseries have corresponding access contact sheets contained in the Contact Sheet series.
    - SXB1-2 – SXB55-12, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - SXB56-12 – SXB128-40, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - SXB129-41 – SXB192-56, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - SXB193-56 – SXB254-80, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - SXB255-81 – SXB321-127, undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - SXB322-128 – SXB385-153, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - SXB386-154 – SXB448-177, undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - SXB449-177 – SXB510-208, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - SXB511-209 – SXB577-228, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - SXB578-228 – SXB648-247, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - SXB649-248 – SXB696-261, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - SXB697-262 – SXB831-335, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - SXB 832-335 – SXB914-360, undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3: Subjects, 1909-1960
    This subseries contains negatives arranged alphabetically by subject. The majority of materials in this subseries are unidentified.
    - Bylar, 1953 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - China, undated (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Cowlik, undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Courthouse, Florence, Arizona, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Mexican Trip, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - McNary, Arizona, 1934 April (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Oblasser, Bonaventure, Color Slide, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Pisinemo School, undated (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - San Carlos, Arizona, 1954 February, June (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - San Ignacio Mission, 1915 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - San Luis Rey Mission, California, undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - San Xavier del Bac (1 of 3), undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - San Xavier del Bac (2 of 3), undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - San Xavier del Bac (3 of 3), undated (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1953 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - St. John's Mission, 1909 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - St. Michael's, 1953 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - St. Peter, Bapchule, Arizona, circa 1950 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Varia, undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified (1 of 16), undated (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified (2 of 16), undated (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified (3 of 16), undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified (4 of 16), undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified (5 of 16), undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified (6 of 16), undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified (7 of 16), undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified (8 of 16), undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified (9 of 16), undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified (10 of 16), undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified (11 of 16), undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified (12 of 16), undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified (13 of 16), undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified (14 of 16), undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified (15 of 16), undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified (16 of 16), undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 4: Glass Negatives, undated
    This subseries contains unidentified glass negatives.
    - Unidentified glass negatives, undated (Box 26)
- Series 5: Nicholas Perschl Papers, 1901-1969
  This series contains papers that relate to the personal life and career of Nicholas Perschl. Included are excerpts from his diary and autobiographical writings for his early years as a missionary; general correspondence from 1901 to 1969, chiefly with other Franciscans, former students, and friends; and letters (in German) from members of his extended family in Austria.
  - Biographical materials, circa 1923-1930 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence, 1901-1969 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with family in Vienna, circa 1905-1948 (Box 27, Folder 3)